Guide to the Jay Katz Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Teaching files, 1961-2001; Series V
  This series consists of papers related to Jay Katz's teaching career at Yale Law School. The files span the full scope of Katz's tenure at Yale Law School from the early 1960s to the early twenty-first century, but there are gaps in the papers, including the entirety of the 1950s, the late 1970s and the early-to-mid 1990s. The papers include class lecture notes, class reading materials, papers related to course proposals and developments, and copies of examinations.
  - Psychopathology, source book introduction and table of contents, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Examinations, 1961-1975 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Lectures and class notes, 1963-1968 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Law and psychiatry program, correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Seminar on informed consent, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Law and psychiatry program, proposals, 1975, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Family law, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Task force, development of a course on professional responsibility for medical students, 1986-1988 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Course on physicians' professional responsibility, 1987-1988 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Materials on professional responsibility, 1988 January (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Procreation and the law of family, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Reproductive technologies seminar, 1999 September (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Proposed bioethics program, 1999-2001 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Writings, 1972-1997; Series VI
  This series comprises scholarly papers and articles written by Jay Katz over the course of his career, though there are some significant gaps in dates, particularly during the 1950s, 1960s and 1980s. The bulk of materials consist of typewritten copies of Katz's writings. In some cases it is specified on a given document whether the copy is a final version or part of a work-in-progress. There are also some photocopies of Katz's published articles, as well as documents related to his publications, including correspondence, reviews, sales figures, and book proposals. There are also several folders pertaining to a proposed book by Katz comparing the Tuskeegee Syphilis experiment with medical experiments conducted at the Dachau concentration camp during World War II. These documents include correspondence regarding the proposal, and drafts of the proposed book's introduction and first three chapters.
  - "Abuse of Human Beings for the Sake of Science", Undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - "Acknowledging Uncertainty: Its Impact on Physicians and Patients", Undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - "Can a Seriously Ill Patient Refuse Treatment? Psychiatrists' Competence to Evaluate Patients' Competence", 1987 May (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Catastrophic Diseases, reviews, 1976-1983 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - 'The Concentration Camp Experiments: Their Relevance for Contemporary Research with Human Beings', 1994 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - 'The Consent Principle of the Nuremberg Code: Its Significance for Then and Now', Undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - 'Decision-Making Between Doctors and Patients', Undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Experimentation with Human Beings, correspondence, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Experimentation with Human Beings, reviews, 1972-1974 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Experimentation with Human Beings and Catastrophic Diseases, sales figures, 1975-1980 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Experimentation with Human Beings, op-ed article, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "Experimentation on Man: The Doctor's Dilemma", 1975 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Guggenheim Foundation application narrative, Undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Hastings Center report on Food and Drug Administration regulations, 1996 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - "Human Sacrifice and Human Research", Undated (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - "Informed Consent to Medical Entrepreneurialism", Undated (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - "Maternal-Fetal Conflicts", 1990 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - "The Nuremberg Code", 1995 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - "Obstacles to Informed Consent", Undated (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - "Procreation and the Law of Family", Undated (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Published articles, general, 1992-1995 (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - The Silent World of Doctor and Patient, proposed revisions, 1996-1997 (Box 17, Folder 22)
  - The Silent World of Doctor and Patient, sample cases, Undated (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - Tuskegee and Dachau, proposed book
    - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Introduction, Tuskegee, Dachau, and Contemporary Research, draft, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Chapter One, The Tuskegee Syphilis Study, draft, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Chapter Two, The Nazi Concentration Camp Experiments, draft, 1992 July (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Chapter Three, In Search of Explanations, draft, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - "The Tuskegee Syphylis Study", 1991 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified research proposal, Undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified writing fragments, Undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Electronic files, 1985-1990; Series VII
  Conditions Governing Access
  Closed until processed.
  Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
  This series consists of fifty-six 5.25" floppy disks. The disks contain an assortment of documents produced by Jay Katz, including speeches, writings, letters of recommendation, and notes. The titles listed in the inventory are transcriptions of the disk titles as assigned by Katz. Some of the disk titles indicate that they may contain duplicate copies of documents already included in Series III and VI.
  - "Discussion of the Case of Mrs. M.B.," speech, Boston University Medical Center, 1986 January 26 (Box 19)
  - Preface to paperback edition of The Silent World of Doctor and Patient, 1985 August (Box 19)
  - Limping is No Sin: Reflections on Making Healthcare Decisions, 1984 May (Box 19)
  - Curriculum Vitae, Undated (Box 19)
  - "Decision Making Between Doctors and Patients," speech, Chicago, 1985 February (Box 19)
  - "Decision Making Between Doctors and Patients, II," speech, Chicago, 1985 February (Box 19)
  - "The Social Medical Origins of the PHS Directive on Human Studies," speech, Houston, 1986 February (Box 19)
  - Recommendation letters, J. Leibowitz, C. Worrell, Undated (Box 19)
  - Family Law, introductory, Undated (Box 19)
  - Eric Cassell, book review, Undated (Box 19)
  - McKay, 1986 (Box 19)
  - "Informed Consent - Are 'Miracle, Mystery, Authority' Better Medicine," speech, Connecticut State Medical Society, 1986 May 8 (Box 19)
  - "The Regulation of Human Experimentation in the U.S. - A Personal Odyssey," speech, Chicago, 1986 May 15 (Box 19)
  - "Discussion of the Cases of Mrs. A. and Mrs. B.," speech, Yale Medical School, 1986 May 3 (Box 19)
  - Untitled memorandum, Undated (Box 19)
  - Benz memo; task force memos, 1986 (Box 19)
  - WNEIP memos, Dr. Miller, Dr. Marans, Dr. Young-Breuhl, Dr. Sledge, Dr. Mayes, 1986 (Box 19)
  - The Inevitability of Poor Communication in Contemporary Physician-Patient Interactions, Undated (Box 19)
  - Notre Dame Law School, 1986 August (Box 19)
  - Mrs. A., Mrs. B., 1986 March 5 (Box 19)
  - Bob Cover, Undated (Box 19)
  - Names, 1986 October (Box 19)
  - Medicolegal Grand Rounds, A Case Study in Decision-Making, Yale Medical School, 1986 December 6 (Box 19)
  - Ford Foundation letter, 1986 December (Box 19)
  - "Informed Consent and the New Reproductive Technologies: Who Speaks for the Child?" Chicago, 1987 May 30 (Box 19)
  - "Can a Seriously Ill Patient Refuse Treatment?", 1987 May (Box 19)
  - "Can a Seriously Ill Patient Refuse Treatment?", 1987 May (Box 19)
  - "What Comes Under the Rubric of a Law and Medicine Course?", 1987 (Box 19)
  - "What Comes Under the Rubric of a Law and Medicine Course?" (large print), 1987 (Box 19)
  - Boston University, Undated (Box 19)
  - "Duty & Caring" (3 disks), 1988 (Box 19)
  - "Can Principles...", 1989 March (Box 19)
  - Material for artificial insemination chapter, Undated (Box 19)
  - Freud biographies, 1988 August (Box 19)
  - Chapter notes, 1989-1990 (Box 19)
  - Freud acquisitions, Undated (Box 19)
  - Anne Frank, Nuremberg code, 1989 (Box 19)
  - Different lists of books and articles (2 disks), 1989 (Box 19)
  - Op-Ed article, 1987 (Box 19)
  - Reproductive technologies, briefs (6 disks), 1988 September (Box 19)
  - List of books at Dr. Katz's home, Undated (Box 19)
  - Ohio, 1988 October 15 (Box 19)
  - Lipton, Ed (evaluation of paper), 1988 November 19 (Box 19)
  - Reproductive technologies (notes for J.K.), 1988 (Box 19)
  - Robert Sedler letter, Boston speech, "Happy Isles", 1988 October (Box 19)
  - "Can a Seriously Ill Patient Refuse Treatment?", speech, Pittsburgh, 1989 February (Box 19)
  - Holocaust, draft 3, Undated (Box 19)